
                                                                         FRICTION
Friction is the force resisting the relative motion of solid surfaces, fluid layers, and material elements sliding against each other.
When surfaces in contact move relative to each other, the friction between the two surfaces converts kinetic energy into thermal energy
 (that is, it converts work to heat).
 This property can have dramatic consequences, as illustrated by the use of friction created by rubbing pieces of wood together to start a fire.
 Kinetic energy is converted
 to thermal energy whenever motion with friction occurs, for example when a viscous fluid is stirred. Another important consequence of many types of
 friction can be wear, which
 may lead to performance degradation or damage to components. Friction is a component of the science of tribology.

Friction is desirable and important in supplying traction to facilitate motion on land. Most land vehicles rely on friction for acceleration,
 deceleration and changing direction. Sudden reductions in traction can cause loss of control and accidents.

Friction is not itself a fundamental force. Dry friction arises from a combination of inter-surface adhesion, surface roughness, surface deformation,
 and surface contamination. The complexity of these interactions makes the calculation of friction from first principles impractical and necessitates
 the use
 of empirical methods for analysis and the development of theory.

Friction is a non-conservative force - work done against friction is path dependent. In the presence of friction, some energy is always lost in the
 form of heat.
Thus mechanical energy is not conserved.
DRY FRICTION:Dry friction resists relative lateral motion of two solid surfaces in contact. The two regimes of dry friction are 'static friction' 
("stiction") between non-moving 
surfaces, and kinetic friction (sometimes called sliding friction or dynamic friction) between moving surfaces.

Static Friction Formula
Static friction is a force that keeps an object at rest. It must be overcome to start moving the object. Once an object is in motion, it experiences
kinetic friction.
If a small amount of force is applied to an object, the static friction has an equal magnitude in the opposite direction. If the force is increased,
 at some point the 
value of the maximum static friction will be reached, and the object will move. The coefficient of static friction is assigned the Greek letter "mu"
 (μ), with a subscript "s".
The maximum force of static friction is μs times the normal force on an object.

force of static friction ≤ (coefficient of static friction)(normal force) maximum force of static friction = (coefficient of static friction)
(normal force)
Fs ≤ μs η , and Fsmax = μs η
Fs = force of static friction
μs = coefficient of static friction
η = normal force (Greek letter "eta")
≤ means "less than or equal to"
Fsmax = maximum force of static friction

Static Friction Formula Questions:

1) A 5500 N force is applied to a sled full of firewood in a snow-covered forest. The skis of the sled have a coefficient of static friction 
μs = 0.75 with the snow.
 If the fully-loaded sled has a mass of 700 kg, what is the maximum force of static friction, and is the force applied enough to overcome it?
Answer: On a flat surface, the normal force on an object is η = mg. Using this, the maximum force of static friction can be found:
Fsmax = μs η
Fsmax = μs mg
Fsmax = (0.75)(700 kg)(9.8 m/(s2))
Fsmax = 5145 kg∙m/s2
Fsmax = 5145 N
The maximum force of static friction is 5145 N, and therefore the applied force of 5500 N is enough to overcome it, and start moving the sled.

Kinetic Friction Formula
Kinetic friction is a force that acts between moving surfaces. An object that is being moved over a surface will experience a force in the opposite 
direction as its movement.
 The magnitude of the force depends on the coefficient of kinetic friction between the two kinds of material. Every combination is different.
 The coefficient of kinetic friction
 is assigned the Greek letter "mu" (μ), with a subscript "k". The force of kinetic friction is μk times the normal force on an object, and is
 expressed in units of Newtons (N).
force of kinetic friction = (coefficient of kinetic friction)(normal force)
Fk = μk η
Fk = force of kinetic friction
μk = coefficient of kinetic friction
η = normal force (Greek letter "eta")

Kinetic Friction Formula Questions:

1) A worker in a stock room pushes a large cardboard box across the floor. The coefficient of kinetic friction is μk = 0.520. The box has a mass of
 75.0 kg, and the worker is exerting
 a force of 400.0 Nforward. What is the magnitude of the force of friction, and what is the net force moving the box?
Answer: On a flat surface, the normal force on an object is η = mg. Using this, the formula can be used to find the force of friction:
Fk = μk η
Fk = μk mg
Fk = (0.520)(75.0 kg)(9.80 m/s2)
Fk = 382.2 kg∙m/s2
Fk = 382.2 N

The force of kinetic friction acting in the opposite direction as the motion of the box is 382.2 N. The net force acting on the box is the sum of
 forces. The two forces 
to consider are the force of kinetic friction acting in the opposite direction as the box's motion, and the force exerted by the worker, which is
 400 N forward. If we define
"forward" as the positive direction, the net force is:
Fnet=Fworker-Fk
Fnet=400.0 N-382.2N
Fnet = 17.8 N
The net force acting on the box is 17.8 N forward.
